<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
<teiHeader xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title>Letter from Michael Ventris to Emmett L. Bennett, December 26, 1953</title>
<author>Michael Ventris</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Encoded by</resp>
<name xml:id="MS">Maria Streccioni</name>
</respStmt>
<sourceDesc>
  <title>Michael Ventris Papers</title>
  <publisher>Program in Aegean Scripts and Prehistory (PASP)</publisher>
  <date>2013</date>
</sourceDesc>
</titleStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Università di Bologna</publisher>
<pubPlace>Bologna, Italia</pubPlace>
<address>
<addrLine>Corso di Digital Humanities e Patrimonio Culturale</addrLine>
</address>
<date>2021​-07​-08</date>
</publicationStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<biblFull>
<titleStmt>
<title> Michael Ventris Correspondence </title>
<author>Program in Aegean Scripts and Prehistory (PASP)</author>
</titleStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Program in Aegean Scripts and Prehistory (PASP)</publisher>
<pubPlace>The University of Texas at Austin</pubPlace>
<date>2013-07-25</date>
</publicationStmt>
<titleStmt>
  <title>King Nestor's four-handled cups. Greek inventories in the Minoan script</title>
  <author>Ventris, Michael</author>
 </titleStmt>
 <extent>pp. 15-21</extent>
 <publicationStmt>
  <publisher>Archaeology</publisher>
  <date>1954</date>
 </publicationStmt>
<titleStmt>
  <title>Weiteres zu den pylischen Sachzeichen</title>
  <author>Sundwall, Johannes</author>
 </titleStmt>
 <extent>pp. 29-35</extent>
 <publicationStmt>
  <publisher>Minos</publisher>
  <date>1952</date>
 </publicationStmt>
 <titleStmt>
  <title>A second inscribed clay tablet from Enkomi</title>
  <author>Dikaios, P.</author>
 </titleStmt>
 <extent>pp. 233-237</extent>
 <publicationStmt>
  <publisher>Antiquity</publisher>
  <date>1953</date>
 </publicationStmt>
</biblFull>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<encodingDesc>
<langUsage>
<language ident="en">English</language>
<language ident="grc">Ancient Greek</language>
</langUsage>
<editorialDecl>
<p>La lettera è stata trascritta cercando di mantenere la divisione in paragrafi e le alternanze tra maiuscole e minuscole nella scrittura dell'originale. Per quanto riguarda le parti in lingue diverse dall'inglese, si è scelto di traslitterare le citazioni in greco miceneo ove ciò non fosse stato già fatto dall'autore, mentre le citazione in greco antico sono state mantenute e trascritte come tali. A margine sono state fornite indicazioni sui riferimenti delle tavolette micenee, le persone citate, le citazioni e gli articoli scientifici menzionati nella lettera e marcati appositamente.</p>
</editorialDecl>
</encodingDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
<!--testo lettera-->
<body>
<p>19 North End, NW3.
26 December 1953</p>


<p>Dear Bennett,</p>

<p>  Coming back today after being away in the country for Christmas, 
the unheated house was considerably cheered by your new letter, with 
the very prompt and kind delivery of the photos for the article. I am 
glad you got the "Glossary" all right: I only had the other copies 
photostatted, so the expense wasn't too unreasonable (it was writing
it out I got heartily sick of, as I expect you do of your own indices).</p>

<p> Thank you too for your comments on the <q>tripods</q>, which are very 
interesting. My first reaction is to rise up in arms about the interpretation of <q>line 1</q>, but I don't want to stick my neck out too far, as
I gather from your remarks that there are other tripod tablets- is that 
right?</p>

<p>  But I can't suppress the feeling that <q>ai-ke-u</q> has the shape of a
man's name, or at any rate a proper name of some kind; and that <q>"horn"</q> 
for these objects isn't quite the right material. <q>&kappa;&epsilon;&rho;&epsilon;&alpha;</q> for <q>&kappa;&epsilon;&rho;&alpha;&alpha;</q>
is, as far as one can judge, a pure Ionicism. But I certainly agree that 
it looks like <q>a-pu ke-ka-u-me-no</q>. I was a bit uncertain about this 
end of the tablet, as I wasn't certain how much was broken off, but 
evidently there's room for no more on the bottom line. Is there a second 
word on the top line? I don't feel entirely bound by the division after 
<q>a-pu</q>, because the scribes don't always seem to be consistent in com-
pounds. (Don't I see an erased division after <q>k-toi-no-</q> on <q>Eb 35.2</q>?). 
And I don't see how the ending of <q>KE-RE-A2</q> can tolerate a preposition 
<q>a-pu</q> governing it. An English crank has suggested to me something like 
<q>"from burnt earth"</q> i.e. earthenware, incidentally. If <q>KE-RE-A2</q> is a 
nominative plural, like the WHEELS words of the same ending, it can still 
go with <q>-me-NO</q> if one assumes an accusative of respect (or part affected). 
Aristophanes says, for instance,<q>&kappa;&alpha;&omicron;&mu;&alpha;&iota; &tau;&eta;&nu; &kappa;&alpha;&rho;&delta;&iota;&alpha;&nu;</q> <q>"my heart 
is burning"</q>. So my guess for this is something like <q>a-pu-ke-ka-u-me-nos 
ske-le-a</q> <q>"charred as to the legs"</q>, the <q>-me-nos</q> going of course with 
<q>t-ri-pos</q>.</p>

<p>  Incidentally, I gather that Georgiev is preparing an attack on the 
"standard" general interpretation of the TRIPODS tablet, in which he 
will produce a highly fantastic translation. As an argument that the 
"tripods" words don't apply to TRIPODS, he maintains that the ideogram 
at the beginning of line 2 is the end of the final sentence of line 1. 
But I am sure if that was the case the scribe would never have bothered 
to double up the last words of line 1 in that way, but would have 
given himself more space on the next line.</p>

<p>  I will leave more discussion of the TRIPODS for the moment. I'm 
jotting down a lot of more detailed comments on your last letter, which 
I hope to let you have in the next month.</p>

<p>  I will shove in my own ideas on TRIPODS line 1 in the <bibl>ARCHAEOLOGY 
article</bibl>, but make it clear that there's room for several divergent 
interpretations.</p>

<p>  I haven't seen a copy of the Mycenae tablets yet, but here's 
the loan of Sundwall's <bibl>MA article</bibl>. I'm not sure about the Enkomi photos; 
Crawford was puzzled about them too, but I think decided in the end that 
they were unretouched. The last line which goes over the edge of the 
reverse is part of the text, not a label. Dikaios sent me another photo, 
which shows the signs listed in a footnote to the <bibl>ANTIQUITY article</bibl>.</p>


  <p>Best wishes for 1954,</p>


    <p>Michael Ventris</p>
 </body>







</text>
</TEI>